As we've seen throughout the course so far.
In NestJS applications everything has its place.
This structured application organization, helps us
manage complexity and develop with SOLID
principles. This type of organization is especially useful
as the size of our application or team
grows. Keeping code organized, establishing clear
boundaries, and having dedicated architectural
building blocks, all with the
separate set of responsibilities.
Helps us make sure that our application
remains easily maintainable and scalable over time.
In NestJS, we have 4 additional building blocks
for features, that we haven't showcased yet!
These are: Exception Filters,
Pipes, Guards, and Interceptors.
Exception filters are responsible for handling
and processing unhandled exceptions that *might*
occur in our application.
They let us control the exact -flow- and -content- of
any or specific Responses, we send back to the
client.
Pipes are typically useful to handle 2
things: "transformations", meaning to transform *input* data
to the *desired output* and "validation", meaning to *evaluate
input data* and if VALID - let it
pass through the pipe unchanged but
if NOT VALID, throwing an Exception.
Guards determine whether a given Request
meets certain conditions, like authentication,
authorization, roles, ACLs, etc.
And if the conditions are met, the requests
will be *allowed* to access the route.
And lastly, interceptors.
Interceptors have many useful capabilities inspired
by the aspect oriented programming technique.
Interceptors make it possible to: 1) bind
extra logic, before or after method execution.
2) Transform the result returned from a method.
3) Extend basic method behavior, 4) and even
completely *override* a method, depending on specific
conditions. For example: handling
something like "caching responses".
So now that we've covered the basics.
Let's dive into all 4 of these new
building blocks, in the next few lessons.