Before we jump into the specifics
of each Nest building block.
Let's take a step back and talk about a few
approaches we can take to bind any of these building
blocks, to different parts of our application.
Basically there are 3 different ways of binding:
Filters, Guards, and Interceptors to our route
handlers - with a bonus 4th
way that's specific to Pipes!
Nest building blocks can be: "Globally"-scoped,
"Controller"-scoped, "Method"-scoped, and the bonus
4th one "Param"-scoped (which as we
said is available to Pipes only).
Note that these different binding techniques give you
granularity and control at different levels in
your application.
Each one does NOT *override* another, but
rather layers each one -on top-.
So be careful on how you implement these.
For example if you have a globally scoped Pipe, it
will be applied as well as any other (Pipe) you
might add.
Whether it's controller-scoped method-scoped etc.
So far in this course we've already seen globally
scoped pipes in action, when we use the
ValidationPipe to help us validate incoming
request payloads, amongst other things.
If we open up our main.ts file.
We'll see that we previously bound the
ValidationPipe globally by calling the `useGlobalPipes()`
method of our `app` instance.
You could see that if we type `app.
use`.
Intellisence shows us corresponding methods for
every other building block available here.
Respectively `useGlobalPipes`, `useGlobalGuards`,
`useGlobalInterceptors`, and `useGlobalFilters`.
Going back to our ValidationPipe here.
One big limitation of setting it up and instantiating
it by ourselves like this, is that we can
*NOT* inject any dependencies here!
Since we're setting it up *outside* of
the context of any NestJS Module.
So how do we work around this?
One option we have, is to set up a Pipe
directly from inside a Nest module using the custom-provider
based syntax, we saw in earlier lessons.
Let's open up our AppModule file and
define something called the `APP_PIPE` provider.
This APP_PIPE provider is a special
token exported from the @nestjs/core package.
Providing ValidationPipe in this manner.
Let's Nest instantiate the ValidationPipe within the
scope of the AppModule and once created,
registers it as a Global Pipe.
Note that there are also corresponding tokens
for every other building block feature!
Such as APP_INTERCEPTOR,
APP_GUARD, and APP_FILTER.
Back to our ValidationPipe.
What if we *don't* want to use it globally?
But some are more specific
like on a certain Controller.
Let's imagine that we want to bind a ValidationPipe
to every route handler defined only within our
CoffeesController.
Let's open up our CoffeesController file and make
use of a new decorator `@UsePipes()` that we
haven't seen yet. This @UsePipes() decorator can be passed
in a single Pipe Class or a comma
separated list of Pipe Classes.
Just like in other scenarios.
There are also corresponding decorators for every other
building block that can be used here as
well.
Named `@UseInterceptors()`, `@UseGuards()`,
and `@UseFilters()`.
Alternatively, you can even pass an
"instance" of a class here.
Take for example providing `new
ValidationPipe()` inside of the decorator.
This is super useful when you want to pass
in a specific configuration object to the ValidationPipe
for *this* exact scenario.
Note that as a best practice try to apply
filters by using classes instead of instances whenever
possible. This reduces memory usage since Nest can
easily reuse instances of the same class, across
your entire Module.
All building blocks can also be Method-scoped.
Imagine that you want to bind
a Pipe to a specific Route.
We can achieve this by simply applying
the same decorator we just saw.
`@UsePipes()`, but on top of the specific
method we want to declare it on.
Let's say we want to add specific validation
to our GET findAll() method, within CoffeesController
. With this setup. This ValidationPipe is *only*
applied to this single findAll() Route handler.
We are already familiar with the 3 different
ways of tying filters, guards, pipes, and interceptors
to our Route handlers.
But as we said, there is a 4th
bonus way - that's only available to Pipes.
And it's called Param-based scope.
Param-scoped Pipes, are useful when the validation
logic concerns ONLY ONE specific parameter.
Let's scroll down to the update method here.
This method takes 2 arguments: the resource "id", as
well as the "payload" required to update the
existing entity.
What if we want to bind a Pipe to the
"body" of the request but not the "id" parameter.
This is exactly where the param
based pipe comes in handy.
By passing the ValidationPipe class reference, directly to
the @Body() decorator here, we can let
Nest know to run *this particular pipe*
-exclusively- for just this specific parameter!
And there we have it.
With these 4 powerful building blocks.
We can now control the flow, content,
validation on anything in our application, globally...
All the way down to a specific
controller, method, or even a parameter.