NestJS comes with a built-in Exceptions "layer",
responsible for processing all unhandled Exceptions
across our application.
When an exception is *not* handled by our
application, it is automatically caught by this layer,
which sends the
appropriate user-friendly response.
Out of the box. This action is
performed by a built-in global ExceptionFilter.
While this base built-in ExceptionFilter can automatically
handle many use cases for us.
We *may* want full control over it.
For example, we may want to add exception logging
or return our Errors back in a different JSON
schema.
Exception Filters are designed
for exactly this purpose!
They let us be in charge of the exact "flow
of control" and the "content" of the Response being sent
back to the client.
Let's create an ExceptionFilter, that is responsible for
catching exceptions that are an instance of
the HttpException Class, and implement our
own custom response logic for it.
Let's get started by firing up our terminal, and
generating a filter class using the Nest CLI filter
schematic, by entering:.
nest g filter common/filters/http-exception
Note that we generated this filter in a /common/
directory, where we can keep things that are *not*
tied to any specific domain.
Let's open up the newly generated HttpExceptionFilter,
and see what we have inside.
As you can see, the Nest CLI generated an
example filter, without any business logic of course.
The @Catch() decorator on top, binds
the required metadata to the ExceptionFilter.
This @Catch() decorator can take a single
parameter or a comma separated list.
This allows us to set up a filter for several
types of exceptions at once if we want it.
Since we want to process all
exceptions that are instances of HttpException.
Let's pass the HttpException
class between the parentheses.
All ExceptionFilter's should implement the
`ExceptionFilter` interface exported from @nestjs/common.
This interface requires that we provide the
catch() method with its indicated method signature.
Also we can see that our class accepts a Type
&lt;&gt; Argument, which indicates the Type of the exception
argument in our catch() method.
Again since we want to process all
exceptions that are instances of a HttpException.
Lets changes this to
All right with all of that setup now
we can implement our custom response logic.
To do this, we'll need to access the
underlying platforms Response\{} object so that we can
*manipulate or transform* it and
CONTINUE sending the response -afterwards-.
So where do we get a
hold of the original Response?
Let's use the second parameter here, "host" which we
can see as an instance of `ArgumentsHost`, and
call the method switchToHttp() on it.
Saving this as the variable
`ctx`, short for "context".
This switchToHttp() method gives us access to
the native inflight Request or Response objects.
Which is exactly what we need here.
Next, let's use this `ctx` variable, and
call the `getResponse()` method on it.
This method will return
our -underlying platforms- Response.
Remember in NestJS, this is Express.js by default,
but could also be swapped for Fastify.
For better type-safety here.
Let's specify the Type as a "Response".
importing this Type from the "express" package.
Now that we have our response.
Let's use the "exception" parameter available to us
in *this* method, and extract 2 things.
The "statusCode", and "body"
from the current exception.
To get the status, we can simply call
the `getStatus()` method as we see here.
Let's also get a hold of the raw Exception
Response, by calling to `getResponse()` method and saving
that to a variable as well.
Since for demonstration purposes - we're trying to
pass back this "original" Error response, we need
to do a little bit of work here.
First we need to test whether the
Response is a String or an Object.
If it's a string we're going to create an Object
and put that String inside of the message property.
Otherwise we're all set in our
exceptionResponse is already an object.
By doing all of this. Our errors will now be
fairly "uniform", and we can (...) spread this error
variable into our final response, which
we'll do in a moment!
Great so now that we have everything we need.
Let's start building our response
*back* that we'll be sending.
First let's set the statusCode for the response we're
going to send back via the `status()` method.
(`response.status(status)`) Lastly we need to
send the `exceptionResponse` back.
Our applications underlying platform is
Express.js, which is the default.
So There are several ways we could do this!
In our case. Let's just
use express's `.json()` Method.
We can simply chain this method after our status()
call (as we see here), and using the (...)spread
operator, we can pass the original Error from
our Exception inside of this .json() method.
As of right now. Our ExceptionFilter here
isn't really doing anything unique yet.
So let's pass in something custom
here along with the original exception.
This way we have something we can look for in
all of our errors to make sure everything with the
ExceptionFilter works!
Let's add a new `timestamp` property and
give it the value of new Date().
toISOString(). Great.
Now with all this in place, let's
bind this global ExceptionFilter to our application.
Since we don't need any external providers, here
we can just bind this ExceptionFilter globally
using the `app` instance in our main.ts file.
Let's head over to the main.ts file
and add it real quick with `app.
useGlobalFilters()`.
Passing in: `new HttpExceptionFilter()` inside.
Now that everything's in place.
Let's test it out by triggering some API errors!
Let's make sure that our app is running in our
terminal, and if not make sure we run: `npm run
start:dev` again.
With our application running.
Let's open up insomnia, and perform a GET request
to a *non existing* resource and purposely make
an Error happen!
Let's hit something like /coffees/-1 where "-1", is obviously
an "id" we don't have in the database.
As we can see the Response came back with
an Error and clearly used our new custom ExceptionFilter!
Since the response contains
our new `timestamp` property.
Perfect. So naturally this exception we
created was a basic example implementation.
But you can see that within this ExceptionFilter, we
could have just as easily used some sort of
Logging Service to track our errors,
maybe even called an Analytics API.
Anything we'd want to do whenever
an HttpException occurs in our application.