Interceptors, have many useful capabilities inspired
by the aspect oriented programming technique.
This technique aims to increase modularity by
allowing the separation of cross-cut and concerns.
Interceptors achieve this by adding additional behavior
to existing code, without modifying the code
itself! Interceptors make it possible for us to:.
1) Bind extra logic before
or after method execution.
2) Transform the "Result" returned from a method.
3) Transform the "Exception" thrown from a method.
4) Extend basic method behavior.
5) Or even completely overriding a method
- depending on a specific condition.
For example doing something
like caching various responses.
All right. So to learn
how interceptors work conceptually.
Let's run through an example use-case where we *always*
want our responses, to be located within a
`data` property (data: response_here).
And create a new interceptor
to handle this for us.
Let's call this
new interceptor WrapResponseInterceptor.
This new interceptor will handle *all* incoming requests,
and "wrap" our data for us automatically.
To get started. Let's generate an interceptor
class using the Nest CLI by entering:.
`nest g
interceptor common/interceptor/wrap-response
Note that we generated this interceptor in the
/common/ directory like we have many times before,
since this interceptor isn't tied
to any specific domain.
Let's open up this newly generated WrapResponseInterceptor
file and see what we have inside.
The Nest CLI generated an example interceptor
for us without any business logic.
Similar to Providers, an Interceptor is
a class with the @Injectable decorator.
All interceptors should implement the
`NestInterceptor` interface exported from @nestjs/common.
This interface requires that we provide
the `intercept()` method within our class.
The intercept() method should return an
Observable from the RxJS library.
If you're not familiar with RxJS.
It is a library for
Reactive Programming using Observables.
Making it easier to compose
asynchronous or callback base code.
RxJS itself is outside of the scope
of what we can dive into here.
Just know that it's a powerful
alternative to Promises or callbacks.
Back to our code. The `CallHandler` interface
here implements the `handle()` method (next.handle()),
which you can use to invoke the
route handler method within your interceptor.
If you don't call the handle() method
in your implementation of the intercept method.
The route handler method *WON'T
be executed at all*.
This approach means that the intercept() method
effectively "wraps" the Request/Response stream -
allowing us to implement custom logic both *before*
and *after* the execution of the final route
handler. All right so we've covered
a lot of theory so far.
Let's add some console.log()'s, to see where
interceptors fit in the Request/Response lifecycle.
Since we've called the console.log()
*before* calling the next.handle() method.
Our "Before..." message should appear in the console
BEFORE the actual route handler is executed by
the framework.
Since handle returns an RxJS Observable.
We have a wide choice of operators we
can use to manipulate the "stream" here.
In this example. We're using the tap() operator
which invokes an anonymous logging function upon
graceful termination of the Observable stream.
But (the tap() operator) doesn't otherwise interfere
with the response cycle at all.
The `data` argument of the arrow function and we passed
into the tap operator here, is in fact **the
response** sent back from the route handler!
Basically think of this as whatever
comes back from our endpoint!
Here. We're just doing a
console.log() to say "After..."
And logging that `data` back as well.
To test it all out.
Let's bind this interceptor
to our application globally.
Let's open our main.ts file and add:
`app.UseGlobalInterceptors()`, passing in
`new WrapResponseInterceptor`.
Great, now.
Let's make sure our application is running in
the background and let's navigate to insomnia and
test any endpoint in our application.
First let's make sure we have
some Coffees stored in our database.
To do so. Let's hit the POST
/coffees endpoint and add a random Coffee.
Perfect. Now let's hit the GET /coffees endpoint
and switch back to VSCode to see those
console.log()'s in the terminal.
As we can see "Before..." was logged.
And *then* "After...", followed by the actual
`value` from our findAll() method, which represents
the /coffees endpoint.
It looks like our interceptor worked!
Let's open up insomnia again,
and test another endpoint.
Let's test (GET) /coffees/1 this time.
This time we should see a single object
following the "After..." log in our terminal.
Great so far so good.
So now that we could see how interceptors
work and their part in the Request/Response lifecycle.
Let's implement our "data wrapper" idea we talked about
at the beginning of this lesson and "wrap"
our Response's inside of a `data` property.
To do this let's replace the
tap() function with the map() operator.
The map() operator takes a value from
the stream and returns a modified one.
Since we wanted to wrap all
responses in the `data` property.
Let's return an object with a key/value of data.
Every time this map() function is called, it returns
a new object with a `data` property filled with
our *original response*.
Remember everything we've done here is mainly for
demonstration purposes but hopefully now you can
see the power of interceptors, and how there's a
potential to do so many other things here:.
Like passing down version numbers,
analytics tracking, etc etc..
All right so let's save all of our changes
open up insomnia and test out this interceptor.
Let's execute any HTTP request and see
what the application sends back to us.
Perfect as we can see, the response was
automatically wrapped in an object within the `data`
property. So wrapping up - in this video we've
shown how interceptors give us an incredible power
to manipulate Requests OR Responses,
without changing *any* underlying code.