So far we've learned how to use Interceptor's
to bind extra logic *before* and *after* method
execution, as well as automatically logging and
*transforming* results returned from route handlers
. Another technique useful for interceptors is to
extend the basic function behavior by applying
RxJS operators to the Response stream.
Let's see this in action with a realistic example.
To help us learn about this concept by example.
Let's imagine that we need to handle
"timeouts" for all of our route requests.
When an endpoint does *not* return anything after a
certain period of time, we need to -terminate-
the request, and send back an Error message.
Let's start by generating another interceptor, naming it
"timeout", and also placing it in the
/common/interceptors folder.
Let's open up this newly generated TimeoutInterceptor,
and add some logic in there.
In our example we want to terminate a
request after a specific period of time.
So let's use the timeout() operator
imported from "rxjs/operators" to achieve this.
To demo this easily, Let's set a
very quick `timeout` of 3000 milliseconds.
This means that when a request is made,
after 3 seconds, the request processing will be
automatically cancelled for us.
To test it out. Let's bind this second interceptor
to our application globally, and since it has no
dependencies, we can add this in our main.ts file.
So let's add our new TimeoutInterceptor
here in our useGlobalInterceptors() method.
Note that we can actually bind multiple Interceptors
here simply by separating them with commas.
Now to make sure that
our interceptor works properly.
Let's open up the CoffeesController file and
temporarily add a `setTimeout()` function in our
findAll() method to simulate a very long delay.
Let's set a timeout for 5 seconds, higher than the
3 seconds we set in our interceptor to purposely
trigger our TimeoutInterceptor.
Perfect. Now let's open up insomnia and execute this
endpoint by making a request for GET /coffees
. As we can see, after 3 seconds.
We received a 500 Error
which means our TimeoutInterceptor worked!
However the Error message we got
back is not really descriptive.
It says "Internal Server Error".
But how could we make
this message more user-friendly?
Heading back to our TimeoutInterceptor again.
Let's chain another operator called `catchError()`
inside of our pipe() method
. The RxJS catchError() operator allows us to
catch all exceptions that occurred within the stream.
In the callback function we provide here we can
check if the error throne is an *instance* of
`TimeoutError`.
Which is also imported from 'rxjs'.
If so, we use a utility function `throwError()`
from 'rxjs' to create a stream which immediately
emits an Error for whatever is passed into it.
Since we want our error message to be more
specific for this scenario, let's use a NestJS class
called RequestTimeoutException imported from @nestjs/common, so
we can throw the correct error
message back to our users letting them know
that the request has actually timed out.
Great. So let's save our changes navigate back
to insomnia and test the endpoint once again.
As we can see. This time we received the
408 response with the descriptive message "Request Timeout"
. So in this lesson we learned how to
add additional superpowers to our interceptors along with some
new tricks from RxJS.
All which are very common scenarios and
helpful in most of our NestJS applications.