A lot of NestJS is built around
a powerful TypeScript language feature called "decorators".
Decorators are simply functions that apply logic.
NestJS provides a set of useful param decorators that
you can use together with the HTTP route
handlers, for example @Body(),
to extract the request.body.
Or @Param(), to pick
a specific request "parameter".
Additionally we can create
our own custom decorators.
Let's imagine that for some reason we want
to retrieve the `request.protocol` from within the route
handler. Normally we would need to inject the
entire Request object with the `@Req()` decorator
into the method definition.
However this makes this particular method harder to test
since we would need to mock the entire
Request object every time we
try to test this method.
In order to make our code
more readable and easier to test.
Let's create a custom param decorator instead.
To get started let's open the /common/decorators
folder, and create a protocol.decorator.ts inside
. Now, inside of this file, let's make
use of the utility function: `CreateParamDecorator` imported
from @nestjs/common to build our custom decorator.
Since we're trying to find the `request.protocol` for
our decorator, we're going to need to retrieve
it from the Request object.
We can retrieve this from the ExecutionContext
we've seen in previous lessons, with `switch
ToHttp()`, and then
calling `getRequest()` afterwards.
Let's simply return `request.protocol`
and we're all set.
Great, now to test our decorator.
Let's open up our CoffeesController file and
temporarily use it on the findAll() method
. Let's add a single console.log() within the method
to log out this @Protocol() parameter, and see
what it gives us.
Let's just save our changes, navigate to insomnia,
and execute a GET /coffees request to see
everything in action. Now let's head back
to VSCode and fire up our terminal.
We could see "http", our protocol,
was logged in the console!
Great it works. We can also pass
"arguments" to our custom decorators if needed.
In this instance our @Protocol() decorator is fully stateless
so there's no reason to pass in any
parameters since there's nothing to configure.
However in more sophisticated scenarios where the
behavior of our decorator depends on different
conditions, we can pass the
`data` argument into them.
For example let's say that we wanted to pass
a default value to the decorator we just made.
Let's just pass a string of
"https", between the @Protocol("https") parentheses.
To access this "value" from
within our param decorator factory.
We can use the `data` argument, the
first argument here we previously hadn't touched.
To make our decorator more self explanatory.
Let's change the argument name to "defaultValue", and
set it to type "string", for better
readability and type-safety.
With this in place.
Now let's see if these values are actually
coming into our decorator, and add a single
console.log(defaultValue) to log out this
default value to our terminal.
Again. Let's make sure to save our changes, navigate
to insomnia, and execute the same GET /coffees
request.
Back over to our terminal again.
We can see the defaultValue "https"
object was logged in the console.
Great!