Guards have a single responsibility.
Which is to determine whether a given
request is allowed access to something.
If the request meets certain conditions,
such as permissions, roles, ACLs, etc..
It *will* be allowed access to that route.
If the conditions are *NOT* met, that it will
be *denied* and an Error will be thrown.
One of the best use-cases for
Guards: is Authentication and Authorization.
For example we could implement a Guard that extracts
and validates a Token, and uses the extracted
information to determine whether the
request can proceed or not.
Since there are many different approaches and
strategies to handle authentication and authorization.
In this video we'll focus on a simplified example
and learn how to leverage Guards themselves in our
projects. If you're interested in learning more
about Authentication itself, check out our separate
Course Extension, which is particularly focused
on the implementation of an Enterprise-grade
Authentication feature, and all of the
complexities that go along with that.
All right. So to learn how Guards work conceptually,
let's create a Guard that is responsible for 2
things:. 1) Validating whether an API_KEY
is present within an "authorization" Header.
2) And secondly whether the route
being accessed is specified as "public".
Let's call this new guard `ApiKeyGuard`.
Let's fire up the terminal and generate
a guard class using the Nest CLI.
Let's enter in: `nest
g guard common/guards/api-key
Note that we generated this guard in the /common/
directory, where we can keep things that aren't
tied to any specific domain.
All right so let's open up this newly generated
ApiKeyGuard file, and see what we have inside.
As we can see the Nest CLI generated an example
guard for us, without any logic inside of course.
Similar to providers.
A guard is just a Class with the
@Injectable decorator which we've seen in previous videos.
One important requirement of guards is that
they should implement the `canActivate` interface
exported from @nestjs/common.
This interface requires us to provide
the canActivate() method within our class.
This canActivate method should return a Boolean,
indicating whether the current request is allowed
to proceed OR denied access.
This method can also return a Response that's
either synchronous or asynchronous, such as a Promise
or Observable.
Nest will use the return value
to control the next action.
If it returns `true`: the
request will be processed.
If it returns `false`: Nest will deny the request.
Looking at the example code the
Nest CLI generated for us here.
We have `return true` hardcoded for now.
This means that currently, every request
will be allowed to proceed!
Just for testing purposes, let's change this line
to `return false`, indicating that every request
should be *denied* access.
And now that our initial Mock Guard is all set.
Let's bind it to our application "globally".
Let's open up the main.ts file.
And add `appUseGlobalGuards()` passing in our
new ApiKeyGuard inside of it.
Great. Let's make sure that our application is
running in the background, and let's navigate to
insomnia and test any endpoint.
As we can see ALL of our endpoints now
respond with status "403 Forbidden Resource", just as we
expected. It worked perfectly.
But right now our Guard is not programmatically
determining anything about our route or the caller
yet. It's simply always returning `false`.
That doesn't make much sense right?
Instead, let's set up our Guard to handle the
scenario we talked about in the beginning of this
lesson.
Which is to "validate an API_KEY that should be
present within each request", but -only- on routes
that are *not* specified as "public".
So how can we get started here.
Well first let's define this
API_KEY that we're talking about.
To make sure that we *never* push
this "secret key" to our git repo.
Let's define the API_KEY
as an environment variable.
Open up our .env file that we created in
a previous lesson and let's add the following `API_KEY`
line.
The API_KEY here is just a random generated String, so
feel free to use whatever you'd like for this
example.
With this in place. Let's head back to our Guard.
Here in our guard. We want to retrieve the API_KEY
from any incoming request that is not labeled as
public. We'll be handling this
public part in a moment.
For our API_KEY. Let's assume that the caller
is passing this key as an "authorization header".
To get the information about
this incoming HTTP Request.
We'll need to access it all from
the ExecutionContext ("context" param), which inherits from
ArgumentsHost, which we've already familiarized yourself with
when we used it with the Exception
Filter.
We can actually use those same helper methods from
before, but this time, to get the reference of
the Request object instead of the Response.
This switchToHttp() method, gives us access to
the native in-flight Request, Response and Next
objects! Which is exactly what we need.
Next we need to call the getRequest() method
on it, which will return our underlying platform's
Request wrapper object.
Remember in Nest this is Express.js By default.
But it could also be swapped for Fastify.
For better type-safety here.
Let's specify the type as a `Request` importing
this Type from the "express" package again.
Now let's use this Request object to retrieve
the "authorization" header from each request, if it's
even there. Lastly, let's compare the authorization
header passed in, with the registered API_KEY
we have stored in our environment variable.
For now we'll simply access the environment
variables using the `process.env` object but ideally
you'd want to leverage
the (@nestjs/config) `ConfigService` instead.
With all of this in place.
Let's open up insomnia and test *any* endpoint in
our application, and see if our Guard works so
far. As we can see our application
responded with the status 403 Forbidden Resource.
Since we didn't pass in any authorization
header especially one with our specific API_KEY.
It looks like our Guard is working perfectly.
Let's try the same API request again but this
time let's add an "authorization" header with the
correct API_KEY.
With this in place.
Let's hit send and call the endpoint again.
Perfect. We've got a 200 Response
back and no error this time!
Our Guard was able to verify that the authorization
header matched our secret API_KEY and we were
allowed access to continue the API request.
So far we've finished setting up the API_KEY
validation functionality we wanted but we still aren't
checking whether the specific route being
accessed is "public" or not.
In the next chapter we'll look at how Metadata and
a few other Nest features can help us achieve
just that!