In the last lesson, we implemented the
first goal for our new Guard.
Which was to verify whether an API token
is present when a route is accessed.
In this lesson we'll be looking at how we
can complete the next piece of functionality we needed,
which was to detect whether the route
being access is declared "public" or not.
How can we declaratively specify which end points in
our application are public, or any "data" we
want stored alongside controllers or routes.
This is exactly where custom
Metadata comes into play.
Nest provides the ability to attach custom
metadata to route handlers through the `@SetMetadata`
decorator.
The @SetMetadata decorator takes two parameters.
First being the metadata "key" that will be used as
the lookup key, and the second parameter is the
metadata "value" which can be any Type.
This is where we put whatever values we
want to store for this specific key.
So let's put this to use,
to learn how it all works.
Let's open our coffees controller file.
Head over to our findAll() method, and
add this @SetMetadata decorator on top.
Making sure it's imported
from the @nestjs/common package.
Inside the decorator.
Let's pass those metadata
key and value parameters.
For our key. Let's enter the String of "isPublic",
for our value let's enter a Boolean of `true`.
This is the most barebones way of setting up metadata
on a route, but it's not actually the best
practice. Ideally we should create our own
decorator to achieve the same result.
This is a much better practice because we will
have less duplicated code, we can reuse the decorator
in multiple places, and a custom
decorator gives us much more type-safety.
Let's improve our existing code and make
our own decorator, and call it `Public`.
First let's create a new folder within
the /common/ directory and call it /decorators/.
Here we can store any other
future decorators we might make.
In this folder. Let's create
a new file called `public.decorator.
ts`.
In this file. We're going to export 2 things.
1) being our metadata "key", and the other being
our new decorator itself, that we're going to call
"Public".
For our key let's `export const IS_PUBLIC_KEY` and
set it equal to the string of "isPublic".
Just like we called it previously.
The benefit of exporting this variable here is that
anywhere we might look up this metadata, we can
now import this variable, instead of using
"magic strings" and accidentally mistyping the name.
Now let's export our decorator by entering `export const
Public`, and setting this equal to an arrow
function (=&gt;), that returns `SetMetadata`.
Inside of SetMetadata(/* here */), just like before we
need to pass in that "key" and "value".
So let's use our IS_PUBLIC_KEY variable and for the
value let's pass in the Boolean of `true`, just
like we did previously.
And that's it! We just made our first decorator!
Next. Let's swap out the code we previously added
in our CoffeesController to use our new decorator.
Let's head back over to that findAll()
method signature and replace the previously added
@SetMetadata expression with this `@Public()` decorator, making
sure to import it from our local
directory.
Perfect. We now have a much more future proof
and easily reusable decorator that we can use
throughout our entire application if needed!
Let's tie everything together and fix
up that ApiKeyGuard to use it.
Currently our Guard returns true or false, depending
on whether the API_KEY was provided with the
request. But now we need to
add our `isPublic` logic here.
We need the Guard to return `true`, when
the isPublic metadata is found, *before* continuing further
and testing whether an API_KEY is present.
In order to access the
routes metadata in our guard.
We'll need to use a
new helper class called `Reflector`.
The Reflector class allows us to
retrieve metadata within a specific context.
This class is provided out of the box
by the Nest framework, from the @nestjs/core package.
Let's inject the Reflector class
here, inside of our constructor().
Now we can use this provider within the
canActivate() method, to retrieve the metadata of our
handler.
Let's add a new variable called isPublic.
With this variable, let's utilize `this.reflector.get()` which
looks up metadata by its "key".
In our case the exported variable `IS_PUBLIC_KEY`,
we just made a moment ago.
Reflector requires a "target object
context", for the second parameter.
In our case we want to target
the *method handler* in our given context.
So let's pass in `context.getHandler()`.
Just for reference.
If you needed to retrieve metadata from
a *Class level*, you'd call `context.getClass()` here
instead. For more information on
Reflector and other possibilities here.
Read more about it in the NestJS documentation.
Okay. Great. Now that we have the value from
our decorator inside of our Guard there's one last
thing we need to do.
If a route is "public".
We can simply skip the validation of the API_KEY.
Let's add a simple if statement
and if isPublic is `true`.
Let's just return true.
And lastly we mentioned earlier that
we shouldn't use `process.env` directly.
So let's fix that and
instead use the ConfigService.
Let's move into the constructor
real quick and inject ConfigService.
With this service injected, we can now
replace the previously used process.env.API_KEY call, with:
`this.configService.
get()` passing in the string of "API_KEY".
Let's save all of our changes and check the
terminal to make sure everything is compiling correctly.
Ok so our Guard is ready, but it looks
like the application *couldn't* bootstrap properly, and it is
throwing some compilation errors!
Well what happened?
Well these errors appeared because we're using dependency
injection *inside of our Guard*, which was
instantiated in the main.ts file.
So how can we fix this?
As we showed in previous lessons.
Global guards that *depend* on other classes
**must** be registered within a @Module context.
Let's fix this real quick, and
add this guard to a module.
And actually let's take it up a notch, and create
a new module for our "common" folder, and we can
instantiate our Guard there.
Let's fire up another terminal window and let's generate
a module and call it common with: `nest g
mo common`.
This will generate a module class where we can
register any global enhancers we might make in the
future including our ApiKeyGuard.
Great. So let's open up this new module and
utilize the custom provider setup we learned in a
previous lesson.
This is where we pass in an object into our
provider's array providing a specific class or key and
then the value to be used for it.
Inside of our @Module() decorator.
Let's add a providers:[] Array, and pass in
an object with `provide: APP_GUARD \}` and `useClass:`
with our `ApiKeyGuard`.
This setup is very similar to using `app.useGlobalGuards()`
that we had in our main.ts file.
But as we said, that option is only available
if our guards *do not* use dependency injection.
Note that there is a way around that, but it
isn't a best practice since you'd have to manually pass
in dependencies.
One last thing here. Let's make sure to import
the `ConfigModule` in the imports:[] Array here so we
can use the ConfigService in our Guard.
Now let's open up our main.ts file and remove
that `useGlobalGuards` line since we don't need it
anymore and save all of our changes.
Let's switch to our terminal window again to
make sure everything can bootstrap properly now.
Great. Everything's compiling again.
Now let's open up insomnia and put
our new Guard to the test.
Let's start by removing the "authorization" header, and
make a GET /coffees request, which we setup
to use our @Public() decorator.
If everything works as expected it
should *not* return a 403 error.
Since our guard *should allow access* to it.
And it worked, great!
Next. Let's try a route that *doesn't* have the
@Public() decorator, like a GET request to the end
point /coffees/1.
Our guard should deny us access to this route since
it is neither public nor are we passing in an
authorization header.
And there it is, 403 Forbidden
- our guard works perfectly!
So to wrap up we covered a lot of ground in
this lesson tapping into a lot of concepts we learned in
previous lessons.
Now we have the additional power to create
our own decorators, and utilize handler metadata, useful
for anything our application might
need in the future.