Pipes have 2 typical use-cases.
1) "Transformation" where we transform *input*
data to the desired *output*,
2) And "validation", where we *evaluate* input data
and if -valid-, simply pass it through
unchanged. If the data is -not valid-,
we want to throw an Exception.
In both cases. Pipes operate on the arguments
being processed by a Controller's route handler.
NestJS triggers a Pipe just
*before* a method is invoked.
Pipes also receive the arguments meant
to be passed onto the method.
Any transformation or validation operation
takes place at -this- time.
Afterwards the route handler is invoked
with any potentially transformed arguments.
NestJS comes with several pipes
available out of the box.
All from the @nestjs/common package.
For example ValidationPipe, which we've seen in
previous lessons, and ParseArrayPipe, which we
haven't seen but it's an extremely helpful Pipe
that helps us parse and validate Arrays.
To learn how we can build our own *custom* Pipes.
Let's create a Pipe that automatically parses any incoming
String to an Integer, and let's call it `
ParseIntPipe`.
Nest already has a ParseIntPipe that we
could use from the @nestjs/common library.
But let's create this basic Pipe for learning
purposes, to help us fully understand the basic
mechanics of a Pipe.
Let's fire up the terminal and generate a Pipe
class using the Nest CLI pipe schematic, placing it
in the common/pipe folder,
and calling it "parse-int".
Note that we generated this pipe in the /common/
directory again where we can keep things that
aren't tied to any specific domain.
Let's open up this newly generated ParseIntPipe
file and see what we have inside.
As we can see the Nest CLI generated an
example pipe for us without any logic inside.
Similar to providers a Pipe is
a class with the @Injectable() decorator.
But all pipes should implement the
`PipeTransform` interface exported from @nestjs/common.
This interface requires us to provide
the transform() method within our class.
This transform() method has 2 parameters.
`value`: the input value of the currently processed
argument before it is received by our route
handling method.
And `metadata`. The metadata of
the currently processed argument.
Whatever value is returned from this transform
function completely overrides the previous value of
the argument.
So when is this useful.
Consider that sometimes the data passed from the
client needs to undergo some change, before this
data can be properly handled
by the route handler method.
Another example use case for pipes
would be to provide default values.
Imagine if we had some required
data fields that were missing.
We could automatically set these
defaults within a pipe.
Transformer pipes can perform these functions by
interposing the transformation function we create -
between the client request -
and the request handler.
This is merely another example.
But the point is to show that there are
many powerful things you can do with pipes.
All right. So back to
creating a custom ParseIntPipe.
Let's start by implementing the actual logic.
First. We can assume that the input value or `value`
is a String so we can change the type from
`any` to `string`.
Next. Let's use the built-in `parseInt()` JavaScript function
to try parsing the input string to an
integer.
Let's add some conditional logic here
in case we see any errors.
If the return value is not a number we
can make sure to throw a BadRequestException, otherwise we
can return the modified value,
which is now an integer!
Perfect.
With this in place we can now
bind our pipe to some @Param() decorators.
Let's open up the CoffeesController file
and navigate to the findOne() method.
Before we do anything here.
Let's add a single console.log() to
log the `id` arguments "value".
Now let's navigate to insomnia and execute
a GET request to the /coffees/abc endpoint.
Note we're going to pass "ABC", a String,
instead of a number like 1 or 10.
Let's switch to VSCode and fire up
the terminal and see what was logged.
As we can see it outputs `NaN` or "not a number".
This means that although our "id" `abc` could not have
been parsed to a number, the find one method
was called with an incorrect argument.
To prevent situations like this.
Let's use our newly created ParseIntPipe
to validate the incoming parameter.
And in case it's not parseable to an
integer our Pipe will automatically throw a validation
exception for us.
So let's pass in our ParseIntPipe as the
second parameter to our @Param('id') here, save our
changes, and test the endpoint again
. Great as we can see this time we received
a 400 error with the message stating that "validation
failed".
As we said Nest comes with this Pipe already,
but hopefully this example showcases the power of
Pipes and how you could implement your own to
do a multitude of useful processes for your
application.