Middleware is a function that is called *before* the
route handler and any other building blocks are
processed. This includes Interceptors,
Guards and Pipes.
Middleware functions have access to the Request &amp;
Response objects, and are *not* specifically tied
to *any method*, but rather
to a specified "route path".
Middleware functions can perform
the following tasks:.
1) Executing code.
2) Making changes to the
request and response objects.
3) Ending the request/response cycle.
4) Or even calling the `next()`
middleware function in the call stack.
When working with middleware, if the current
middleware function does not end the request/response
cycle.
It *must* call the `next()` method, which
passes control to the next middleware function.
Otherwise the request will be
left -hanging-, and never complete.
So how can we get
started creating our own middleware.
Custom Nest middleware can be implemented in
either a Function or a Class.
Function Middleware is "stateless", it can *not* inject
dependencies, and doesn't have access to the
Nest container.
On the other hand. Class Middleware can
rely on external dependencies and inject providers
registered in the same module scope.
In this video we'll focus
on building a Class Middleware.
But remember you can always use
Functions to create them as well.
Let's fire up the terminal and generate a middleware
class using the CLI and let's call it
"logging". Note that we generated this middleware in
the /common/ directory again since it isn't
tied to any specific domain.
Let's open up this newly generated LoggingMiddleware
file and see what we have inside.
As we can see the Nest CLI generated
an example middleware without any logic inside.
Similar to Providers in Middleware is
a Class with the @Injectable() decorator.
All middleware should implement the
`NestMiddleware` interface exported from @nestjs/common.
This interface requires us to provide
the `use()` method within our class.
This method, does not
have any special requirements.
Just remember to *always* call the `next()` function
otherwise the request will be left hanging.
For now we'll keep things simple, let's just
add a console.log() before invoking the next() function
to see how middleware fits
into the Request/Response lifecycle.
With this in place we can
now register our newly created middleware.
As we've mentioned earlier middleware aren't
specifically tied to any method.
We can't bind them in
a declarative way using decorators.
Instead we bind middleware to a
route path, represented as a String.
To register our LoggingMiddleware.
Let's open up our CommonModule file.
First let's make sure that our
CommonModule class implements the NestModule interface.
This interface requires us to provide the
`configure()` method, which takes the MiddlewareConsumer
as an argument.
The MiddlewareConsumer provides a set of useful
methods to tie middleware to specific routes.
Just to test it out. Let's apply the LoggingMiddleware
to *all* routes, using the Asteriks *, or
"wildcard operator".
To add our middleware.
Let's call the `apply()` method on
`consumer`, passing in our `LoggingMiddleware`.
And then let's call the `.forRoutes(*)` method,
passing in the wildcard Asteriks *.
Let's save our changes, and navigate to insomnia
and perform an HTTP request to *any* endpoint.
Let's go back to VSCode and see
if anything popped up in our terminal.
Great. We can see "Hi from
middleware" String in our console.
Now taking a step back
to our middleware `consumer`.
There are several other ways of
tying middleware to different route paths.
So far we've bound the LoggingMiddleware to *every*
route using the Asteriks * wild card.
But we could also apply only to routes with,
let's say the "coffees" prefix if we want.
We can even restrict middleware further if we'd like
let's say to a particular Request Method like
only for `GET` methods, by passing an object containing
the route path and request method like so.
Note that we imported the Request method Enum we
used in previous lessons to reference the desired
request method type.
Lastly we can also -exclude- certain routes from
having the middleware applied with the `exclude()`
method. This method can take a single
String, multiple Strings or a RouteInfo object.
Identifying routes to be excluded.
For example we can apply the middleware to every
route -except- for those with the "coffees" prefix
if we wanted.
Now that we've looked at a few
of the options available to us here.
Let's revert back to our original `forRoutes(*)`
wildcard since we want to bind the
LoggingMiddleware to *every* existing
endpoint for now.
Let's open up the LoggingMiddleware file again
and add some additional functionality in here.
For a fun example, let's calculate "how long"
the entire request/response cycle takes, by using
console.time().
Note that this calculation will include the
Interceptors, Filters, Guards, method handlers etc.
that this route may have as well!
In this example we're hooking into the Express.js
Response "finish" event so we know when our
console.timeEnd() should occur.
Let's save our changes and navigate to insomnia.
Now let's execute a random HTTP request to
our application, and head back to the terminal.
As we can see there's a new request/response
message indicating that the full round-trip took a
roughly 23 milliseconds.
This was all a basic example, but hopefully this
shows you the potential that middleware brings to
an application.
For a more realistic use case you could potentially
utilize something like what we just created, to
log "long lasting methods" to a database, and keep
track of how long every API takes to complete.